Never forget why you are the church.
But if you would turn your Bibles to Romans chapter 9.
Romans chapter 9, if you're new, I don't typically dress like this.
This is a once a year situation.
It does also hurt my feelings every
single year because this is what happens.
So everyone comes up and like, man, I love
your suit and if they're new, they're like, man, this is awesome.
This is great.
And if they've been here long enough, this is what they say.
I can't believe that still fits.
I mean, that's ridiculous.
Let me just tell you something.
It still fits.
This is about the 10th time I've worn it.
And so we're going to keep it and 10th time is in like once a year.
the only thing I just wear it and wear it 10 times the last, you know, month.
But either way, it's always fun.
Actually, I debated on whether to wear it this
year or not, I was like, man, I'm 30 now.
I probably need to, you know, do some more grown up
things, but guess what happened?
I'll put it on.
Amen.
But either way, today we're going to close out Romans chapter 9.
Now remember the theme and context of chapter 9 really
flows through chapter 11.
So we're going to kind of, you know, we're going to see a flow
in a theme, thematic context that is
not going to end until we get to chapter 12.
And then at chapter 12, it kind of shifts
to a more practical message and lesson
from Paul.
But if you want some information that
and talking about chapters and verses,
If you want some information that you may not have known, the original manuscripts
of God's Word did not have chapters and verses.
It was just one continuous writing.
As a matter of fact, books like Romans were letters meant
to be read in their entirety.
Now, could you imagine, if I said today, we're gonna read Romans?
Would y'all like that?
I know I know AV team wouldn't like that because that'd be
a lot of slides, amen?
But listen, if you want to know
the history of it, chapters were not actually introduced to the
1300s and versus not until the 1500s,
that being said, I do appreciate, I am thankful for
the chapters and verses of the Bible.
But we have been looking at the doctrine of mercy.
Again, remember the difference between mercy and fairness.
Society foolishly desires, a fair God.
They want everyone to go to heaven because, well, that is
just fair.
And we see that in our culture and society that we live in.
Everyone wants the days of if
you don't work, you don't eat, they're long gone.
Everyone should have what everyone else has because that's fair.
Well, that's not how life works.
Amen?
And there's actually a very big issue with that
line of thought.
See, the issue is no one deserves eternal
life with Jesus.
Our sin made it that way.
Therefore, if God was fair, we would all go
to hell for eternal torment.
So we don't want a fair God.
We want a merciful God.
Mercy is God not giving us what we deserve.
Again, we deserve help.
We deserve judgment.
Our sin is enough for us to be condemned, but God, who
is rich in mercy, made a way through his only begotten son, Jesus,
so that we cannot be condemned, but forgiven and delivered.
So we ought to thank God for his mercy.
Amen.
God's mercy, however, was a complicated concept to
the Jewish people of Paul's day.
So far, we have gone over the people of mercy.
We've gone over the plan of mercy and we continue this
morning with the paradox of mercy.
Let's pray.
Father, again, I thank you, Lord, for your word.
And God, I pray that I'm faithful to your word this morning.
God, I pray those that have ears to hear.
May they hear.
Let me preach this with power, clarity, and freedom.
God, I pray that we with soft hearts receive with gladness.
God, we thank you, we love you.
Thank you for your mercy.
In Jesus name, pray.
Everybody said, amen.
Really, this started in Romans 9, verse 6, not as though the word
of God had taken that effect.
For they are not all Israel, which are of Israel.
In other words, it's not that God's word had failed.
But the Israelites, that time, the Jewish community
at that time, they would say, but we are Israel.
How can we not be his children if I am an Israelite?
I can tell you what tribe I come from.
I can tell you my heritage.
There's no way that I could be lost because I am of Israel.
And then Paul says, but that's not the case.
See, Paul here is speaking of national election.
He did choose Israel over Edom.
That is Jacob over Esau, not for salvation,
but rather for who would be the covenant heir.
As a matter of fact, knowing knowing how God is and
knowing that his character never changes.
I want you to know that if Esau would have received the
mercy of God and received and put his faith in Jesus,
put his faith in God, I believe, according to scripture, Esau could have been saved.
Did you miss that?
That's a big deal right there.
See, we look at scripture, we say, okay, well, you know, that
just means that Esau never had a chance.
No, no, no, no, no.
Esau could have experienced God's goodness and given his life over.
But if you study him, he didn't.
Jacob would be renamed Israel and have 12 sons.
These 12 sons would make up 12 tribes that
we know as the 12 tribes of Israel.
These tribes make up what we know today as the nation of Israel.
I do want us to know that God's promise and covenant
he made with Abraham all the way back in Genesis 12.
According to scripture is an everlasting covenant.
In other words, it is not going to end.
Do not let the news media.
Do not let all these different articles on Facebook, not let all these
people that don't know scripture from scripture tell you that God
has changed his mind.
God does not change his mind when he makes a promise.
And that's why this chapter is so important.
National election is not the same as personal salvation.
And that's the paradox Paul is explaining here.
Do we see this in our culture today?
Of course we do.
I cannot tell you how many times I've asked somebody, if they
know Jesus, and this is their response, well, my dad was a deacon.
Well, bless you, brother, you know what I'm saying?
My uncle is a preacher.
My grandma led WMU for 30 whole years, preacher.
Yeah, I'm good.
Don't worry about me.
Well, here's the thing.
That fine and dandy.
And that's really cool that your family loves the Lord supposedly.
But that's not what I asked.
Do you know Jesus?
You know, answering like that is like bragging about your heritage, right?
People say, and there's certain people that love to brag.
Anyone know anyone that loves to brag about their heritage like you don't know who I'm related to?
My lineage goes all the way back to George Washington.
Yep, that one, the one, the 1st president, George Washington.
This is how I responded to that.
Did he leave you land, money, or any cool possessions?
If not, who's thinking cares?
I mean, that's how I look at that.
I can tell you what my lineage goes back to.
His name is Adam.
And he was a dirty sinner just like me.
But now my lineage has changed through Jesus.
I am a new creation.
Hear me?
My past, forgiven, and my future security.
Isn't that a beautiful thing that we have with Jesus.
What about you, though?
So getting back to the text at hand.
Paul uses Old Testament again to nail
his point even further.
So if you're in Romans chapter 9.
Let's look at verses 25 through 29.
If you're there, say read.
As he saith also in Hosea.
I will call them my people, which were not my people.
And her beloved, which was not beloved.
And it shall come to pass that in the place where it was
said unto them, you are not my people, there shall,
there shall they be called the children of the living God.
Isaiah also cried concerning Israel, though the number of
the children of Israel be as the sand of the sea, a remnant shall be saved.
For he will finish the work and cut it short in righteousness because
a short work will the Lord make upon the earth.
And as Isaiah said before, except the Lord of Sabbath
and left us a seed, we had been as Sodom
and been made like unto Gomorrah.
Now here we're going to break this down, you're going to kind of understand it.
By the way, that Sabaoth means almighty, the host.
That means the might of God.
So that's talking about God himself.
But Paul quotes 2 prophets.
The 1st of which is Hosea.
Specifically Hosea chapter one, verse 10,
and Hosea chapter 2, verse 23.
This is where he demonstrates the adoption of those who are far from him.
This is all in the context of spiritual
restoration of Israel.
God tells Hosea.
If you haven't read Jose, I'm going to kind of summarize it for you.
God tells Hosea, a man, and a prophet of God.
That's what who Hosea was.
We know him as a minor prophet just because the,
you know, the work, his work was a little bit shorter, but he
was a prophet and a man of God.
God tells him to marry a harlot named Gomer.
Now, that doesn't make sense, does it?
I mean, let's just think about that.
He's telling God's man, go marry a prostitute.
They had 2 children that God told to be named,
lo, Rahama, and lo, ah me.
If you think those are odd, just wait until you find out what they mean.
Lo, Rahamama,
Mama, Mama.
Mercy.
She has not obtained compassion.
Can't say her name, no mercy there, right?
No compassion.
Lo on me means not my people.
Now, usually name giving is a special thing.
Amen?
You put a lot of thought on that.
Let me just tell you something.
That's not a joyful announcement of names.
However, this was to symbolize Israel's unfaithfulness to God.
Gomer, the one who Hosea had
delivered from a life of prostitution, ended up
leaving him and going back to sinful, wicked ways.
What did Israel do time and time again to God?
God would deliver them from their enemies.
And over time, they would once again live in idolatry, and
in the ways of those nations surrounding them.
Now, you think of this situation, you think, okay, well, you know what?
Hosea, try, God told them, go get Gomer, marry
her, make you, make her your wife, have children with
her, name your children these things.
I've commanded you to do so.
Gomer leaves, and you might be thinking, well, you know what happened?
Hosea did what he was supposed to do?
Good riddance.
She's back.
whatever.
I'm done with her.
But that's not how it went at all.
God told Hosea.
This is the beautiful part about it.
Go back and get her again.
Look in Hosea chapter 3.
We're going to read the whole stinking chapter, 5 verses.
It says this.
Then said the Lord unto me, go yet.
that means go again.
Love a woman, beloved of her friend, yet an adulterous,
according to the love of the Lord, toward the children of Israel,
who look to other gods and love flagons of wine.
So I bought her to me for 15 pieces of silver, and
for when Homer, barley, and a half Homer of barley.
And I said unto her, thou shalt abide for me many days, thou
shalt not play the harlot, thou shalt not be for another man, so
will I also be for thee.
For the children of Israel shall abide many days without a king.
And without a prince, and without a sacrifice, and without
an image, and without an Ephod, and without a teraphim, of
afterwards shall the children of Israel return and seek the Lord their God, and
David their king, and shall fear the Lord, and his goodness in
the latter days.
Remember, he's talking about the restoration of Israel here.
Why?
Because God promised Israel an everlasting promise.
God is showing his enduring faithfulness.
Now I want to pause to take a little moment here.
This is to be taken for an example.
However, this really actually happened.
Hosea really took Gomer,
the prostitute, as his wife.
He really had her family with her.
She really left him for her old ways and her old life.
And he really went back and redeemed her again.
This actually happened.
Sometimes we read scripture, and we don't realize that
we are reading about actual people, that it actual things.
You say, why in the world does this matter?
Marriage is in the room.
What God joins, let no man put asunder.
Now, listen, I'm not saying things don't happen.
I'm also not trying to shame people who have been divorced and separated.
Oh, I'm trying to tell you is what God thinks about it.
We have put these contingencies on marriage.
Well, I love her and I am faithful to her, but if she did
this, I would just have to leave.
And it goes both ways.
Let me let me remind you of what we have done and
continue to do daily to God.
We sin against him daily.
We have an affair against God daily
with our idolatry in our life.
We play the harlot with our worldly desires and ambitions,
yet time and time again, he keeps us.
He loves us.
He stays with us, and he comes back and gets us.
We would do good to stop putting the, if they do this, messing
our marriages in love like Jesus did.
Let me just tell you something.
You know, that's not easy.
Don't you love how preachers get up and say what you should do and act like it's easy?
It's not easy.
I don't think Hosea, when God said, go back and get her.
He just got excited, said, oh, yeah, let me go back and get her.
I'm pretty sure Jose was probably like, what are you talking about?
This woman done left me.
This woman's over here sleeping with all kind of men.
This woman.
no, no, no, no.
She broken the covenant.
There's no way I can go back and get her.
He saying, no, no, no, you've got to show how I love y'all.
Go back and get her.
All I'm trying to say is this.
When Jesus said, forgive 7 times 70.
He is not saying it forgiveness number 491 to be done with them.
Y'all with me this morning?
Okay, let me know every now and again.
This is in marriage in every part of our life.
And the reason why I'm saying this and putting
this in here is because the enemy is
trying to attack our marriages.
The enemy is trying to attack our home.
And what happens when they do is all of a sudden,
you'll start thinking, well, that I deserve this or, oh,
well, well, this is something that cannot be forgivable.
We have to look at how Jesus forgave
us the unforgivable.
God is faithful to Israel, even when they were not faithful to him.
But in this restoration, he does something no one saw coming.
Romans 9 again, verses 25 to 26,
as he saith also in Hosea, I will call them my people, which
were not my people, and her beloved, which was not beloved.
He's quoting Hosea here, and it shall come to pass it in the place where
it was said unto them, you are not my people.
There shall they be called the children of the living God.
He in this restoration of Israel.
He invites the Gentiles in.
In other words, he invites us in to the promise.
In Romans 11, he calls it grafting them into the tree.
And it took Israel's rebellion and rejection to bring it about.
As a matter of fact, Romans 11, verse 11 says,
I say then, had they stumbled that they should fall.
God forbid, but rather through their salvation through
their fall, salvation has come unto the Gentiles for
to provoke them to jealousy.
I want you to know, church, God's ways are higher than our own every
single time.
I want to tell you that if you think, well, I don't really agree with that plan.
Well, then you're wrong.
I don't know if I said this Wednesday or last Sunday.
If you disagree with God's word,
hear me out.
I want to softly land this punch right here.
You are wrong.
You need to change your mind because guess what?
You're not outsmarting the Lord.
You don't know something that God doesn't know.
Your plans are not perfect.
Your plans are not higher.
Your plans are not holier.
You are wrong.
I am so sick and tired of people looking at scripture
and saying, yeah, I just don't believe that.
Well, you don't believe correctly.
So get right.
Sorry, we'll continue.
But again, Paul moves to the prophet Isaiah.
He goes from Hosea to Isaiah.
Look at Romans chapter 9, verse 28 through 29,
for he will finish the work and cut it short in righteousness, because
a short work will the Lord make upon the earth.
And as Isaiah said before, except the Lord, Sabbath
had left us a seed.
We had been like Sodom and been made like unto Gomorrah.
What happened to Sodom and Gomorrah?
They were destroyed.
See, he is quoting Isaiah chapter 10, verse 22 and
23, and also chapter one, verse 9.
Here, Paul is re-emphasizing that God keeps his promises.
God kept his promise to Abraham and that his seed
was as countless as the sands of the sea.
Yet only a remnant would be saved.
And that remnant is what is being spoken of about in
Romans 9, verse 29.
You can see there, it says, unless he had left us a seed,
that word seed can be translated a remnant.
If God, this is what he's saying, if God had not restrained
the enemies of Israel, if he would have simply
allowed what they deserved to happen to happen,
Israel would have been like Sodom and Gomorrah
utterly destroyed.
But that's not what he had promised.
Therefore he left a remnant.
So to answer the question from verse six, not as though the word of God had taken that effect.
In other words, has God has God's word failed.
The answer is no.
God's word has not failed.
It is through his great mercy that we are chosen.
It is by his grace that we are saved.
What a mighty God we serve.
Now, he finishes this chapter with another question.
Look at Romans chapter 9, verse 30.
It says this.
What shall we say then?
I love when Paul starts off with this because you know
he's about to just give you just some truth right here.
What shall we say then?
What now?
What does all this even mean?
Well, this is where we move from the paradox of mercy to the
pursuit of mercy?
Romans chapter 9, verse 30 through 33.
I know we're reading a lot, but it's good.
You're going to catch up on the devotes that you skipped all week.
Amen?
What shall we say then?
That the Gentiles, which follow not after righteousness,
have attained to righteousness, even the righteousness, which is of faith?
But Israel.
which followed after the law of righteousness had not
attained to the law of righteousness.
Wherefore, because they sought it not by faith, but
as it were by the works of the law.
But they stumbled at that stumbling stone, as it is written,
behold, I lay in Zion, a stumbling stone, a rock of
offense, and whosoever believeth on him shall not be ashamed.
Now, just to get some clarity, okay?
I want to read this in the NSB 95, because it kind of clarifies
some scripture here.
What shall we say that the Gentiles who did not pursue
righteousness attained righteousness,
even in righteousness, which is by faith, but Israel pursuing
a law of righteousness did not arrive at that law?
Why?
Because they did not pursue it by faith, but as
though it were by works.
They stumbled over the stumbling stone, just as
this is written, behold, I lay in Zion, a stone of stumbling and
a rock of offense, and he who believes in him will not be disappointed.
This is really where the rubber meets the road.
Here is the declaration of obtaining mercy.
How could the Gentiles who have never received the law?
Never fall after righteousness.
Never knew the oracles and prophecies of God, yet
they attained righteousness.
How could this be?
Well, the Bible says because they pursued it by faith.
I want you to think about the reference verse from last week.
In Acts 13, Paul and Barnabas is preaching in
the synagogue to their fellow Jews.
This is what they declare to them in Acts
chapter 13, verses 40 and 41.
It says this, beware, therefore, lest that come upon
you, which is spoken of in the prophets.
Behold, ye despisers and wonder and perish.
For I work a work in your days a work which ye
shall in no wise believe, though a man declare
it unto you.
In other words, what Paul and Barnabas is warning them is this.
They are warned to not be like those before who rejected
the word and work of God.
We are declaring the truth to you, believe and receive.
Well,
I guess that didn't do anything.
So they had church kind of like Cedar Grows, have church, the preacher preaches, and everyone just leaves.
Amen.
So the Jewish folk left the synagogue.
Well, what happened there?
One verse 42.
And when the Jews were gone out of the synagogue, the Gentiles
besought that these words might be preached to them, the next Sabbath.
Y'all miss that?
I think some of you did.
And when the Jews were gone out of the synagogue.
The religious people.
The people that were always there.
The people that were just going to church because it was church time.
When they left, the people that were deemed unworthy,
unrighteous, dirty, wicked outside of
the promise, came in and said, hey, can you preach that to us?
Could you imagine?
At Cedar Grove, all of you leave, and all of a sudden,
as your cars are leaving, people who have been touched
by God are entering and saying, hold on, I
know we weren't here at 1030, but can you preach it again?
We want to hear the good news.
That's pretty good.
Now, that word besought means this.
Ask for earnestly, beg, plead.
They were pursuing the truth.
They wanted to hear the preaching of the gospel.
But then we see if we just continue down a line that some of the Jews
did believe in continuing the faith.
In verse 43.
Now when the congregation was broken up, men of the Jews and religious proselytes,
follow Paul and Barnabas, who, speaking to them, persuaded them
to continue in the grace of God.
So remember, again, it's not a total rejection of the Jews.
It's not a complete blindness and numbness of the Jews.
National election is not the same as individual election.
There was obviously some Jews, some religious proselytes that
followed the faith, continued in his grace.
But then the next Sabbath day came.
Now remember, the Gentiles said, hey, next Sabbath, can you preach that to us?
Well, next Sabbath day comes.
Look at verses 44 and 46 in that same chapter, Acts 13.
And the next Sabbath day came, almost the whole city
together.
to hear the word of God.
In other words, almost, and I made a
joke last week, I'm going to say it again.
Almost the whole city.
People stayed home.
People didn't come, but almost the whole city.
That had been a lot of people.
Almost the whole city came to hear the word of God.
Why did they come to hear the word of God?
Can I tell you something?
Listen, I believe the church is a is a is a whole situation.
In other words, we need worship.
We need fellowship.
Right?
We need to break bread together.
We need the Lord's suffer.
We need to have baptisms.
We need to minister.
We need to do all these things.
But you do realize if we do all these things and the word of God is not preached,
we're not, what are we doing?
When we come together in the way we have, right?
And I'm not saying every time that we go and do a ministry here in ministry there,
deliver gift bags or that, that I got to stand behind a pool pit and preach to people.
That's not what I'm saying.
What I'm saying is when we have gathered this morning, notice
that everything has been built up for the word.
Almost the whole city came to hear the word of God.
But when a Jew saw the multitudes.
They were filled with envy.
and spake against those things which were spoken by Paul contradicting and blaspheming.
You know, we do that today, don't we?
Let me tell you how.
is a church down the street.
Not a particular church, just down the street.
That could be any church in Lebanon.
know what I'm saying?
Church down the street.
Oh man, they had a bigger crowd today.
Oh, yeah, well, they probably just, you know, they probably compromised.
We have a small crowd because we stand on the truth.
No, maybe because you're boring.
I don't know.
Oh, no.
I mean, listen, if half the congregation is sleeping, it's pro-
I mean I don't, you know?
But still, we get jealous, we have envy.
And so we start talking about each other.
The churches do.
Oh, well, we do it better.
We do it like this.
Listen, hey, think about it.
The Jews saw the multitude.
And we're jealous.
that people are hearing the word of God.
And they started contradicting him blasphemy and they were trying to stop the work
that God had started.
Well, Paul and Barnabas waxed bold when that happened.
Look at verse 46 and said it was necessary that the word of
God should have 1st been spoken to you.
But seeing ye put it from you.
In other words, seeing that you reject it.
And judge yourselves unworthy, hear what he's saying.
Unworthy of everlasting life.
We turn to the Gentiles.
So what we have here is a church service.
Almost the whole city shows up.
This consists of Jews and Gentiles, obviously.
But when the Jews saw the crowds, they were not happy, so they
were angry, and they began to attempt to sabotage the message of the gospel.
Paul and Barnabor saw this and made the clear and concise turn
to bring the gospel to the Gentiles.
And when the Gentiles heard the good news, what happened?
Well, verse 47 through 49.
For so hath the Lord commanded us saying, I have set thee to be
a light of the Gentiles, that thou shouldest be for
salvation unto the ends of the earth.
And when the Gentiles heard this.
They were glad and glorified the word of the Lord.
And as many as were ordained to eternal life, believe, and
the word of the Lord was published throughout all the
region, church, they pursued mercy and received it.
Even though they did not previously know the law or traditions,
they now knew and followed Jesus Christ.
the fulfiller of the law.
That is a stunning contrast to those who had received the law.
Remember, it says, but Israel and Romans chapter 9, but Israel,
which followed after the law of righteousness, had
not attained to the law of righteousness.
Wherefore?
Why?
Because they sought it not by faith, but as it were by the works of the law.
For they stumbled at that stumbling stone.
As it is written, behold, I lay in Zion, a stumbling stone and a rock of a fence.
And whoever whosoever believeth on him shall not be ashamed.
See, this is what we are still struggling to grasp in the church today.
We all want Jesus.
en?
I mean, if you know anything about Jesus.
You want Jesus.
I mean, I don't know.
I couldn't imagine somebody just not wanting Jesus, right?
Now we all need Jesus.
Amen.
We all want eternal life.
Amen?
Just keep saying amen until I'm done with this part, okay?
We all want mercy.
But here's what happens.
We're done with that part.
Here's what happens.
We would rather follow a list of rules.
than a truly Wahu God.
We have a, I believe, what I was told, and that's enough mentality.
But do we understand that faith penetrates every part of our life?
See, you gotta understand something.
Our faith is what fuels us to serve God.
Our faith is what fuels us to worship him.
It's what fuels us to obey him.
Hear me.
You can obey the law for a time without faith, but it's only going to be a time.
You'll fall right back into your sin.
It takes faith.
Why do we want to follow a list of rules rather than walk
with God in an intimate fellowship way?
Well, because here's the thing.
If we follow a list of rules, I can show you what
I'm doing and I can point out what you're not.
What does that do?
That makes me look better and you look worse.
And see, that's what we've done in churches.
As long as I'm not living as bad as this personal over here, I'm good.
Let me just tell you something.
Your sin that nobody knows about.
is just as bad as the sin that everybody knows about.
As a matter of fact, someone who is open with their sentence says,
hey, listen, I know that I'm a sinner and I struggle
and I need help and I need Jesus and I need some accountability.
I need some discipleship.
Let me just tell you something.
God's gonna use that person way more than someone says, oh, I'm good.
Don't worry about me.
I've got all my ducks in a row spiritually.
Come on.
Now, we're going to see this in scripture here.
Church, without faith, it is impossible to please God.
Israel, the Jewish people, they knew all about Jesus, but
did not have faith in Jesus.
They stumbled over him rather than received him.
Have you ever stumbled over something you refused to handle and deal with?
No, let me remind you then.
Has anybody ever not cleaned something up the floor, maybe in their
bedroom, and you forget about it, then you get up in the
darkness and trip over it?
Is that is that literally just me?
Is that just me, Philip?
Whatever, man.
So let me tell you what happens with me.
Right?
Right now, you know, the girls, they're in that time where they like
to just throw everything everywhere.
You know what I'm saying?
Just do everything everywhere.
Everything.
Everywhere.
We literally took up our, oh, I have a story.
Don't have time for it.
I'll tell you later.
We took out our oven.
Okay?
And I cannot tell you the amount of gumballs.
that was under my oven.
I mean, it was almost disgusting.
I could have picked them up and sold them.
Like, it was the craziest thing ever.
But everything's everywhere.
So, so when we do this, and, and, and, you know,
I know some of y'all, y'all have to eat, um, at the table and,
and, you know, with the fork and a knife and and say you're these and
thou's to each other and and have a little, no, we like to chill out
in a room and eat pizza and watch TV.
You know what I'm saying?
that's what we like to do, you can judge me later.
But when we do that, we make them clean up.
And so when they clean up, they go get the broom.
And see, they clean up, and what they do is, man, it's the most, it's the most,
it infuriates me.
So they take the broom and they clean it up in a little pile.
And they laid a broom on the pile.
I'm like, listen, pick that up.
They're like, we will.
You ever done that?
I will.
They won't.
and they don't.
So you know what happens?
Here's what happens.
I get up in the middle of the night.
It's dark out.
Why?
Because it's the middle of the night.
And I get up and man, what I do?
I stumble over that broom.
Now, I'm not as old as Philip.
So I can recover quickly from a stumble.
Amen.
It's what you get anyway.
Now, why am I making this silly story?
What he's trying to say is, Jesus is right in front of him.
Preaching the word of God.
The Messiah had come.
Right there, he is.
And they stumbled over him.
They refused to put their faith in him.
And if you look at the church today, we do the same thing.
We have many religious, traditional Bible thumping, self-righteous
people who call themselves followers of Christ, but they have stumbled.
Over the law.
Ephesians 2, 8, and 10, for by grace are you saved through faith,
and that not of yourselves, it is the gift of God, not of works, lest
any man should boast, for we are his workmanship created in
Christ Jesus unto good works, which God happy foreordained
that we should walk in them.
Notice the order.
We are saved by grace through faith, grace being a free gift
of God, and in being saved, by
grace through faith, we are able to live out the good works that God
has before ordained, that we should walk in them.
It is the greatest plan ever made, and God invites us in on it.
But what we do is we reverse the order.
We say I do good works, therefore, I'm saved.
If that's you here today, I want with all my heart and the love
and compassion, you're lost if you've not put your faith in God.
Well, preacher, if Israel can miss it, surely I can miss it.
Throughout the past several centuries, the Orthodox tradition
of Christianity has had what has been called the Jesus prayer.
This is a prayer that models humility and sincere worship before God.
Many different variations have been used.
It's kind of like what we would call the sinner's prayer, but a different in a different way.
But the most often recorded from this all throughout the centuries
has been this, Lord Jesus Christ, Son of God, have mercy on me a sinner.
That's the Jesus prayer.
That a prayer of humility.
See, Jesus tells a parable regarding this in Luke chapter 18.
And starting in verse nine, you just hear me, and he spake
this parable into a certain which trusted in themselves that they were
want, that they were righteous and despised others.
In other words, exactly what we're talking about here in Romans 9.
They trusted in the law.
They trusted in their own works and despised anyone else.
Two men went up into the temple to pray.
The one a Pharisee and the other a Republican.
Now, let me give you some backstory here.
Pharisee, religious elite, right?
This Pharisee, man, they would do all the things, they would be on, in all
the gossip, they would they would make sure everyone saw they give, right?
They were religious, elite.
They were the top dogs in the religious organization.
But then you have a publican.
Now, a publican was like a tax collector.
Now, I don't know if you like the IRS?
No one likes the IRS.
So in other words, the publican was a very hated person.
Why?
Because they were very commonly dishonest.
Hey, you might have owned 50, but they're going to say you own 75.
They're going to keep the 25 for themselves.
You can't do anything about it because they're backed by the Roman government.
You understand what I'm saying?
So people despised the wickedness and
the sinfulness of a publican.
So you have a Pharisee, a religious elite,
the one who looks the part, knows the part, talks the part, and
you have a publican who lives in sin.
The Pharisee stood and prayed thus with himself.
God, I thank thee, that I am not, as other men,
are extortioners, unjust adulterers, or even as this publican.
I fast twice in the week.
I give ties of all that I possess.
And the public can stand afar off.
Would not lift up so much his eyes unto heaven,
but smote upon his chest saying, God be merciful to me, a sinner.
You see the difference there?
I tell you, this man went down to his house justified rather than the other.
For everyone that exalted himself shall be abased.
He that humbles himself shall be exalted.
And they brought unto him also infants that he would touch them.
But when his disciples saw it, they rebuked them, and this is when he
brought the humble kids in and blessed them.
But here's the thing.
We talk about the Jesus prayer.
We have one person that thinks, well, because I do this and do this and
do this, I'm better than the person who does it, but the person
who knew their sin, they struck their chest,
say, God be merciful, and to me, I am a sinner.
One went home with mercy and one didn't.
Now this does not justify sinful living.
You do understand when you put your faith in God, everything changes.
The things that you once lived in, 1st off, you're
not going to get away with it because you got what's called the conviction of the Holy Spirit.
That word conviction means pain.
Listen, if you're a believer and you can sin without pain, something is wrong.
You need to go back and visit with Jesus because here's the thing.
We ought to be, we ought to be so sensitive to sin,
that every little sin hurts us.
Why?
Because we know that we're hurting our Father in heaven.
We see this Jesus prayer with the blind Bartimaeus
in Luke 1838, and he cried saying, Jesus,
thou son of David, have mercy on me.
You know what the disciples did?
Hush, Barn Maeus.
Hush, Jesus is busy.
You know what Jesus did?
Went and healed them.
The 10 lepers in Luke 17, 13, and they lifted
up their voices and said, Jesus Master, have mercy on us.
You know what society did?
Exile on him.
Get out of here.
you dirty, you're filthy, and they were.
You know what Jesus did?
He healed them.
Why is it so important?
Church, if you are looking for mercy from God,
God has already done everything needed for you to attain that mercy.
Call upon him.
All we have to do is put our faith in him.
Now, I know we're talking about elect and chosen and this and that,
but and you might be saying, well, well, preacher, what if I'm not one of the elect?
The American preacher and journalist, Henry Ward Beecher, summarized it well.
The elector whose ever will, and the non-elect or whosoever won't.
So will you or won't you?
If you're here today,
And you need mercy.
And you know that you're a sinner lost in need of Jesus.
What's keeping you from crying out, God?
I'm a sinner, have mercy on me.
Maybe you're here today.
and you're a believer.
And you've you've kind of falled away a little bit.
And you're starting to think, well, I know I'm saved, but I'm good.
Let me just tell you something.
You can be saved and our fellowship with the Lord.
But the victory comes when you're in fellowship with the Lord.
So maybe you even today had to pray the same prayer.
God have mercy on me.
I'm a sinner.
Will you?
Well, won't you?
Has bound eyes closed over this place?